<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>WEBSAUR</title>
    <link>/authors/bjorn/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/bjorn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>WEBSAUR</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Bjørn Peare Bartholdy, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 15:45:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/authors/bjorn/avatar_hu0db20e5b253746b1d4433d50c98117c3_48139_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>WEBSAUR</title>
      <link>/authors/bjorn/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build-a-Calculus</title>
      <link>/talk/aapa2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/aapa2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study presents a model calculus system, which will allow experimental research to be conducted on in vitro dental calculus. We grow oral multispecies biofilms on plastic pegs, which are inoculated with whole saliva and suspended in artificial saliva for 25 days. The mineral composition of the in vitro calculus was verified using FTIR spectroscopy and archaeological and modern reference calculus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biofilms were submerged in solutions (0.5% w/v) containing wheat and potato starches twice daily for six minutes. Over the course of the experiment the biofilms were exposed to a large quantity of wheat (ca. $45.43×10^6$) and potato (ca. $3.583×10^6$) starch grains, of which only a minor proportion was visible, microscopically, in thecalculus (0.0021% and 0.0018%, respectively). The proportion of small (&amp;lt;20 µm) grains recovered from the calculus for both wheat (0.0034%) and potato (0.0032%), was greater than for large (&amp;gt;20 µm) grains (0.0003% and 0.0007%, respectively). These results suggest that only a minor portion of an individual’s diet is retained in the dental calculus and that there is a size bias in the incorporation of starches, such that larger grains may be underrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model calculus system can provide the framework to perform controlled experiments addressing fundamental questions and issues concerning dental calculus, which have yet to be explored. These include validation of sampling and extraction methods, the incorporation of dietary and other markers into the calculus matrix, and the effects of taphonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was funded by the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program [grant number STG–677576 (“HARVEST”)].&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to basics</title>
      <link>/talk/isba2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isba2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, analysis of dental calculus has experienced a surge in popularity due to its ability to store and preserve markers of past diet. However, little is known about the processes by which these markers are incorporated into the dental calculus, and to what extent the data obtained by various methods (e.g. aDNA analysis, palaeoproteomics, and microscopy) are an accurate depiction of past diets and behaviours; if they have unidentified sources of bias causing that would cause under- and overrepresentation of some markers, or others to be missed entirely. The primary objective of this study was to develop a protocol for a model calculus system that can provide a means of testing the accuracy of current methods used for the extraction and analysis of dietary markers, and address future questions pertaining to dietary research on dental calculus. Dental plaque was grown for 10 days based on the ACTA active attachment (AAA) biofilm model, and then mineralised for 10 days using a calcium-phosphate-monofluorophosphate-urea (CPMU) solution. Known quantities of starches were added to the calculus during daily &amp;ldquo;feedings&amp;rdquo;. These were assessed to evaluate the extent of incorporation of starches in the dental calculus, the efficiency of extraction protocols, and the accuracy of microscopic analysis of starch quantities. Multiple replicates of dental calculus samples were successfully grown, each containing ca. 12 mg of calculus, demonstrating the efficacy of this method for creating a model calculus system. As expected, the overall number and ratio of starches decreased over the course of extraction, dissolution in EDTA and/or HCl, and analysis by microscopy. The dietary image depicted by the final starch quantities was inconsistent with the quantity and ratio of starch that was originally &amp;ldquo;fed&amp;rdquo; to the calculus. There remains a lot to learn about the incorporation of dietary markers in calculus, both ante-mortem and post-mortem, and the biases of various analytical methods. The in vitro model calculus system presented here provides a controlled environment for assessing the loss of calculus due to potentially biased sampling and analysis methods, contributing valuable information to facilitate the most efficient methodological approaches to future research questions on diet and dental calculus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
