<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | WEBSAUR</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Bjørn Peare Bartholdy, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu5b8ab339ac96d7ddbeb25f9ec9ced7d5_27764_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spit, Tartar, and Burial</title>
      <link>/post/spit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/spit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experiment forms a portion of my PhD project looking into various aspects of dental calculus (tartar) and diet. Starch grains are found in many food products and can become entrapped in dental calculus. This allows researchers to recover information about the food that was consumed in the past, as the starch grains can often be identified as elements of wheat, oat, barley, etc. However, we know little about how starch grains end up in calculus, and how much of the dietary behaviour of an individual in the past is actually encapsulated within the ancient dental calculus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the experiment is to mimic archaeological conditions and determine how well starch grains survive in the soil when protected by calculus, and how much dietary information will be lost over time. Artificial dental calculus will be grown in the lab and “fed” with solutions containing potato and wheat starches twice daily for three weeks. The calculus will then be buried for periods of 3, 9, and 18 months, to document what happens to the starch grains within the calculus when they are in the ground. Once the samples have been excavated, they will be dissolved in a weak acid and analysed under a microscope to determine the quantity of starch grains remaining in each sample. The samples will be compared to control samples that are not buried, and will give some indication of the degradation of starch grains over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;link to original post: &lt;a href=&#34;https://leidenarchaeologyblog.nl/articles/spit-tartar-and-burial-an-experiments-diary&#34;&gt;https://leidenarchaeologyblog.nl/articles/spit-tartar-and-burial-an-experiments-diary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
